Guide to The University of Montana Associate Dean of Students Records 1918-1973
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
University of Montana Associate Dean of Students records
1918-1973
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
RG 017
University of Montana Associate Dean of Students
2.5 linear feet
The collection contains materials from the women’s student organizations overseen by The University of Montana's Dean of Women, Associate Director of Student Personnel Services, and the Associate Dean of Students.
Historical Note
The Dean of Women position was started at the University of Montana in 1907 with Mary Stewart as Dean. Originally, the Dean supervised the students at the university who lived at the women’s dormitory. The Dean of Women became responsible for the administration of the activities, social life, and counseling of the university’s women students. Harriet Rankin Sedman was appointed Dean of Women in 1921 and served in the position until 1935. Sedman initiated several campus organizations and traditions, including Mortar Board, Spur, and Lantern Parade and organized the Association of Women Students and Big Sister movement. Mary Elrod Ferguson served as Dean of Women from 1935 until 1946.
Maurine Clow became Associate Director of Student Personnel Services, a position which superseded that of Dean of Women, in 1946. The title of the position changed to Associate Dean of Students in 1948, although the job responsibilities did not change. Clow became advisor to student organizations that were once the responsibility of the Dean of Women, such as the Spurs, Junior Sponsors, Alpha Lambda Delta, the Mortar Board, the Miss Montana Program, and many others.
The collection contains materials from the women’s student organizations overseen by The University of Montana Dean of Women from before and after the position was replaced by the positions of Associate Director of Student Personnel Services in 1946 and the Associate Dean of Students in 1948. The collection contains minutes, manuals, reports, scrapbooks, photographs, and other materials from the following women student organizations: Mortar Board, Alpha Lambda Delta, Panhellenic, Junior Sponsors, and the Miss Montana State University Pageant.
Materials are arranged by student organization.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives & Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The source and date of acquisition of these materials by the Archives is unknown.
During processing, national publications were removed from the collection. Panhellenic pamphlets from The University of Montana found in the collection were moved to University Publications.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.). Associate Dean of Students--Archives; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.)--Administration; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.)--Students--Social life and customs; University of Montana (Missoula, Mont.)--Students--Societies, etc.; State University of Montana (Missoula). Dean of Women; Montana State University (Missoula). Dean of Women; Montana State University (Missoula). Associate Director of Student Personnel Services; Montana State University (Missoula). Associate Dean of Students
Deans (Education)--Montana--Missoula; Women college students--Montana--Missoula--Social life and customs; Women college students--Montana--Missoula--Societies, etc; Deans of women--Montana--Missoula
Montana; Colleges and Universities; Student Life
- University YWCA [Young Women’s Christian Association], minutes, 1925-1927 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Mortar Board, minutes, 1918-1956 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Mortar Board, minutes, 1949-1954 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Mortar Board, minutes, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Mortar Board, minutes, 1954-1957 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Mortar Board, history, undated (Box-folder 1/6)
- Mortar Board, suggested service projects, 1946-1956 and undated (Box-folder 1/7)
- Mortar Board, calendar and uniforms, 1949-1958 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Mortar Board, Annual Reports, 1929-1956 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Mortar Board, service reports, 1927-1940 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Panhellenic, miscellaneous, 1936-1944 and undated (Box-folder 2/1)
- Panhellenic Council, meeting minutes, 1937-1943 (Box-folder 2/2)
- Panhellenic Council, minutes, 1943-1949 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Panhellenic Meeting Agendas, 1946 and undated (Box-folder 2/4)
- National Panhellenic Conference, manuals and reports, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Alpha Lambda Delta, scrapbook, 1941-1951 (Box-folder 2/6)
- Alpha Lambda Delta, membership rolls, 1936-1972 (Box-folder 2/7)
- Alpha Lambda Delta, scrapbook of alumnae correspondence, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3/1)
- Alpha Lambda Delta, 1936-1955 (Box-folder 3/2)
- Alpha Lambda Delta, 1956-1971 (Box-folder 3/3)
- Junior Sponsors, 1947-1955 (Box-folder 3/4)
- Junior Sponsors, 1956-1970 and undated (Box-folder 3/5)
- Junior Sponsors, photographs, 1956-1957 and undated (Box-folder 3/6)
- Montana Heritage of Spurs, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
- University of Montana women and student groups, 1956-1964 and undated (Box-folder 4/1)
- Women’s housing, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 4/2)
- Miss Montana State University Pageant, clippings, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 4/3)
- Volunteer Center, 1969-1971 and undated (Box-folder 4/4)
- Volunteer Center, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 4/5)
- Dance and luncheon photographs, 1956, 1964, and undated (Box-folder 4/6)
- Miscellaneous, 1957-1973 (Box-folder 4/7)
- Alpha Lambda Delta, Montana State University Chapter, 1936 (Box-folder OS 5)
- Women students, scrapbook, 1944-1950 and undated (Box-folder OS 5)
- Turner Hall scrapbook, 1962 (Box-folder OS 5)
- Associated Women Students scrapbook, 1963-1967 (Box-folder OS 5)